（桐山(きりやま) 零(れい)）また来てしまった
Yet here I am.
（川本(かわもと)あかり）キャー！
Really? Are you sure?
いいの？ 本当に？
Fwap
ああ これで
何日分の食費が浮くかしら
How many days of food expenses will we save from this?
This is wonderful! Thank you!
よかった　ありがとう！
We got extravagant for New Year's,
so she told us to be frugal for a while.
（川本ひなた）お正月
ぜいたくしちゃったから—
しばらく質素にねって言ってたの
But now we can have delicious food starting tomorrow!
でも これで あしたからも
おいしいものが食べられるなぁ
Warm
We'd already finished eating.
今日は もう
みんな食べちゃったんだ
Those are the leftovers, but I hope that's okay.
残り物ばっかりだけど
いいかな？
Yum!
D-Delicious!
（零）うっ… うまー！
Th-The egg rice is delicious!
た… タマゴかけごはん うまーっ！
Hey, Rei. Can you sleep with me tonight?
（川本モモ）
ねーねー 零ちゃん
今日は モモちゃんと一緒に寝よ
That's a good idea!
いい考え！
Let's do that! After all, tomorrow's Saturday.
そうしなよ あした土曜だし
僕 今日は
帰らないといけないんだ
I have to go home tonight.
Why? Let's stay here together!
えー 何で？ 一緒にいようよ
Why? Why, why, why?
どうして？
何で？ 何で 何で…
（零）モモちゃん　僕ね—
Momo.
I've got a match coming up that I just can't lose.
今度 どうしても
負けたくない試合があるんだ
So I have to go home and study.
だから おうちに帰って
勉強しないといけないんだ
お勉強？
テストがあるの？
Study? Do you have a test?
Yes, that's right.
そう　そうなんだ
どれだけ頑張ったかを—
It's a test where I show my opponent
and myself how hard I've been trying.
相手にも 自分にも
見せるテストなんだ
Momo.
じゃあ 零ちゃんに
言ったげないと
You have something you need to tell Rei.
Tell him what?
何て？
あのね 零ちゃん
テストなんだって！
Um, Rei says he has a test.
Right. So what do you say at a time like this?
そう！ こういうときは
何て言うのかな？
You say, "Do your best."
“頑張って”って言うんだよ
Rei, do your best!
零ちゃん　頑張って！
I will.
はい
I'll do my best.
頑張ります
The sound of a train running alongside a river
The color of sunflowers blooming facing down
The sunset becomes a striped border
Why do I want to cry every time you say "thank you"?
I'm like a child
I thought I'd left all my tears in the fridge
Red rover, red rover, send that girl right over
Goodbye, bystander
We keep walking
Even if at the end of this road isn't Heaven or anything like that
I just want to keep being with you and smiling together
Pride, wishes, and hope
I'll always have them just like you do
When you're scared, so scared, and becoming depressed
I'll protect you, I'll always protect you with everything I have
I promise you to your face
Black River (Part 2)
（三角(みすみ)龍雪(たつゆき)）うっ！
All right,
（三角）さて… 行くか
time to go?
After that, I spotted Kiriyama just once at the shogi hall.
（三角）あのあと 一度
将棋会館で桐山を見かけた
一心に 棋譜を調べ
控えを取っていた
He was looking at match records and making copies of them.
I was going to talk to him,
話しかけようかと思ったが—
but then I saw that stern look on his face and stopped.
その険しい表情を見てやめた
Kiriyama had been gathering the match records for Shimada, 8-dan, and Gotou, 9-dan.
桐山が集めていたのは—
島田(しまだ)八段の棋譜と後藤(ごとう)九段の棋譜
その二つだけだった
Just those two.
Sheesh. The little punk.
（三角）…ったく あのクソガキ
Man, that pisses me off. What a jerk.
（三角）いやー 腹立つわ あの野郎
He's totally ignoring the possibility that I could win?
俺が勝ったケースは
思いっきりスルーかよ
And he expects to crush Shimada, then move right on to Gotou?
そして 島田さんすら
ぶっちぎって—
もう後藤と当たる気満々って
何様のつもりだよ
Who does he think he is?
俺には ねーよ
I can't imagine myself beating Gotou and then facing off against Shimada.
後藤を破って 島田さんと
向かい合うビジョンなんて
だけど 分かってる
But I understand.
そうだ　そこが問題なのだ
That's right.
That's what the problem is.
What Kiriyama sees isn't just a
selfish figment of his imagination.
桐山の見たビジョンは—
ただの虫のいい思い込みとも
また違う
We're professionals.
俺たちはプロだ
Whether I accept it or look away,
deep down I measure my own ability with cruel precision.
受け入れようが目をそらそうが
自分の力量は—
残酷なまでに正確に
胸のどこかで測っている
Measuring that is what it means to be a professional.
それが測れてこそのプロだ
There are some people who think, "I may win,"
勝てるかもしれないと
思える人間が そのまま—
勝つ可能性のある人間
だったりするのだ
and there's a possibility that they will win.
But not me.
俺には ねーよ
後藤を破って 島田さんと
向かい合うビジョンなんて
I can't imagine myself beating Gotou and then facing off against Shimada.
つまり そういうことだ
And that's how it is.
However, trudging on and sidling up to victory
from that point is also part of a professional's job.
だが しかし…
そっからも 更に生き汚く
勝ちに にじり寄ろうとするのが—
また プロの仕事って
やつなんだよね
後藤の形は 居飛車穴熊(いびしゃあなぐま)
対する俺は 風車
Gotou often uses a Static Rook or Bear in the Castle opening.
In response, I'll use the Windmill opening.
If Gotou is heavy and stiff, I'll be light and expansive.
後藤が“重く堅い”とすれば—
俺は“軽く広く”が持ち味だ
All right, please begin.
The calm mind
is the way
（記録係）
それでは 始めてください
Let's have a good match.
（後藤正宗(まさむね)･三角）
よろしくお願いします
（三角）後藤と戦うのは２度目だ
This is my second time playing against Gotou.
Last time, to prepare for a drawn-out battle against Gotou's strong defensive position,
前回は 後藤の重厚な囲いから
長期戦になると覚悟し—
I also strengthened the defense around my king,
こちらも玉(ぎょく)の囲いを厚くしたが—
but the nimbleness I always put my faith in
was weakened by the armor it wasn't used to,
慣れない かっちゅうに—
身上(しんじょう)であった身軽さを
そがれた形になり—
結果は惨敗だった
and the result was a crushing defeat.
そして それを踏まえ
さんざん対策を練った上で—
Based on that, I've come up with a number of countermeasures.
This time, I've decided to face him with what I excel at.
今回は 自分の得意な形で
ぶつかることを決めた
俺は あまり玉(ぎょく)を囲わず
素早く動き回り—
I won't shield my king much,
and I'll move the pieces around quickly,
making countless small wounds and stealing his vitality.
小さな傷を無数につけ
相手の体力を奪う
Against that...
対する後藤は—
じっくり堅く囲って
重たい一撃を狙ってくる
Gotou will make a firm, measured defense,
and then attack me with a single massive strike.
If that strike hits me, it's over.
その一撃を食らったら最後だ
I can't let my concentration slip an inch.
１ミリも集中を欠くことができない
But I'm ready to do this.
だが やってやろうじゃないか
A match in which victory and defeat is completely decided beforehand
100パーセント
勝敗が決まっている対局もまた—
doesn't exist between professionals.
プロ同士 絶対に無いのだ
The sky looks dark, like it'll rain.
（女性職員）やな空　雨が降りそう
Actually, on the news they were saying it'll snow tonight.
（男性職員）いや 夜から
雪だって言ってたよ　予報では
No wonder. I thought it was especially cold out.
（女性職員）道理で…
すごく冷えると思った
（三角）どれだけ体力があるんだ？
Just how much vitality does he have?
I keep wounding him, but he won't crumble.
いくら傷をつけても崩れない
つけ込む隙が無い
There are no openings to attack.
I've drawn a lot of blood, but he hasn't flinched.
このくらいの出血では
ビクともしない
Conversely, my moves aren't getting very far right now.
それどころか
俺の手が伸びなくなった
And then,
そして その一撃がきた
that one strike came.
Sacrificing his rook for my silver?
飛車(ひしゃ)を切って銀(ぎん)を？
What the hell is he doing?
何てことしやがる！
What is...
この男 何が見えてる
this man seeing?
He's attacking me with tremendous force.
ものすごい力で攻め込まれる
He'll pry me open!
こじあけられる
Pitch-black water is rushing in.
真っ黒な水が
一気に流れ込んでくる
I can't breathe...
息が… できない
Just like that, I'm getting dragged down...
あっという間に
引きずり込まれていく
to the bottom.
みな底まで…
And there's nothing I can do.
なすすべが無い…
（三角）負けました
I lost.
You were light.
軽いな
But still a little heavy.
だが まだちょっと重い
After I did B-2f, you defended with G-5b from the left.
２六角(かく)とのぞいたあと
５二金(きん)左と守ったな
You should've gone up to 6c instead.
６三金と
上がった方が良かったな
あれで重さが出てしまった
The way you did it, the heaviness came out.
Lightness is your creed, right?
身軽さが身上なのだろう？
If so,
ならば…
don't hesitate.
迷うな！
（三角）あ〜あ ざまぁねえな
That was pathetic.
Not only was it a helpless, complete defeat, but my delusions were shattered as well.
なすすべ無く完敗したあげく
つきものまで落とされて
A full course, huh?
フルコースかよ
Don't hesitate.
（後藤）迷うな！
What's the deal with that overbearing manliness?
（三角）何なんだよ
あの分厚い男っぷりは
How old is he?
いくつよ？
Forty-one?
41？
Will I be able to project that kind of punch in ten years?
あと10年ちょっとで
出せんのか 俺　あの迫力
モテんだろうな
I bet he's popular with the ladies.
Damn, now I'm getting pissed off.
あ〜あ 何か
すげー腹立ってきた
All right. For the rest of the night...
さってっと
とりあえず今日のところは… だ
Course A: if it goes in,
I drink my cares away at the usual hostess pub.
Ａコース
入ったら お姉ちゃんのいる店で
飲んだくれる
Course B: if I miss, I go home,
get under the covers, and then sob.
Ｂコース
外れたら うちに帰って
布団かぶってワンワン泣く
Rustle
Bonk
Gasp!
（ネコ）ミィー
S
h
i
v
e
r
S
h
i
v
e
r
S
h
i
v
e
r
S
h
i
v
e
r
S
h
i
v
e
r
S
h
i
v
e
r
S
h
i
v
e
r
S
h
i
v
e
r
S
h
i
v
e
r
Could it be?
これは…
Perhaps a Course C?
よもやの Ｃコース？
Course C:
Bring a
stray
cat home
and take
care of it.
Course C:
Bring a
stray
cat home
and take
care of it.
Shrink
Mew...
What should I do?!
どうする 俺？
（ネコ）ミィー
Okay, already! I get it!
（三角）だー もう
わーったっ つーの！
ミー ギャ！
ミャウ ミャ〜
Okay, okay. Stop meowing.
（三角）ああ もう
鳴くな 鳴くな
仕切り直しだ
We'll start over.
You and me both, from square one.
（三角）俺もお前も 一からな
（ネコ）ミィ
Black River (Part 2)
Hey.
You look well.
元気そうじゃないか
Too bad.
残念だよ
そっか…
I see.
このままいくと お前とも
当たることがあるってわけか
At this rate, you and I will end up going head-to-head.
Well, I'm looking forward to that.
まっ 楽しみにしてるよ
It should be a little more interesting
than beating you with my bare hands.
素手で殴るよか
もちっと面白そうだしな
あっ そうだ
That's right.
お前から 幸田(こうだ)のオヤジに
言っといてほしいんだけど—
I want you to pass on a message to your old man.
It's about that stalker woman.
あのストーカー女のことだけどさ
早くやめさせるようにって
Tell him to get her off my back.
She's really annoying.
迷惑してんだよね 俺
You know?
On the Other Side of the Door
He was provoking me.
（零）挑発だ
I know that.
分かってる
But...
でも… やるしかない
I have to do it.
First, I have to deal with today.
それには まず今日だ
Nothing will start unless I win today.
今日 勝たないと何も始まらない
Shimada Kai, 8-dan.
島田開(かい) 八段　Ａ級在位５年
Five years in Class A.
I've been looking at a lot of his match records, but it's strange.
いくつも棋譜を並べてみたが…
不思議だ
I can't find any distinctive features.
特徴が見えてこない
Strategies he prefers, holes in his play...
得意戦法も苦手なものも
I can't pinpoint any.
つかみどころが無い
I haven't played against him before.
対局したことはない
But wait...
でも そうだ
小学生のころ—
When I was in elementary school, he was a guest speaker at a children's shogi tournament I attended.
子供将棋大会の中の
イベントで—
講師で来ていたのを
見たことがある
He was awfully thin and tall, and I remember he spoke quietly.
ひどく痩せてて背が高くて
静かに話す人だった
I'd had a winning streak, so I just watched from afar.
僕は 勝ち進んでたから
遠くから見ただけで—
He didn't really make an impression on me.
あまり印象に残ってないけど
Instead of playing to win, he's someone who plays not to lose.
勝つ将棋というより
負けない将棋を指す人だ
こういうタイプの人との対局は
長くなるな
Matches against people like that are usually drawn-out battles.
I'm not a fan.
苦手だ
But...
でも…
I can't let him get under my skin.
イライラしたらダメだ
そこに食らいつかれる
That's where he'll eat me alive.
Stay calm.
冷静に
Gotou just gave it to me.
（幸田香子(きょうこ)）
もらったばかりなのよ 後藤に
I can't lose here.
（零）ここで
負けるわけにはいかない
No matter what.
どうしても
I played black this match.
対局は 僕が先手(せんて)　相矢倉(あいやぐら)になった
We both developed a Fortress defense.
ここまでは 定跡(じょうせき)どおり
It's been standard moves up to now.
All right, time to start the battle.
さあ開戦だ　いくぞ！
Here I go.
R-5b?
５二飛(ひ)？
全部 受け切るつもり… か
Does he intend to block everything?
In that case...
なら…
He moved his gold back a square.
金(きん)を引いた
Does he plan to move the rook around?
飛車(ひしゃ)を回るつもりか？
じゃあ 俺もだ
Then so will I.
Somehow...
何だか…
it's hard for me to move.
指しにくいな
In this situation,
こういうときは 玉を堅く囲って…
it's a good idea...
to surround the king.
Surround...
囲って…
Wait a second.
ちょっと待てよ
Something's wrong.
おかしくないか
I was supposed to be attacking.
攻めていたはずだよな
And yet,
なのに…
いつの間にか守りになっている
somewhere along the way, I started defending?
What is this?
何だこれ
いつの間に こんなに悪く…
When did the situation get this bad?
I didn't... make any mistakes.
ミスは… 無かった
無かったはずなのに
I didn't, and yet...
And yet, what is this?
なのに何だ？
This...
この…
この厳しさは
This intensity?
I can't...
攻める手が… もう無い
attack anymore?
Crap!
くそっ
Knight
（島田 開）はぁ… やれやれ
Jeez.
You finally look this way.
やっと こっちを見たな
Shogi
Hall
（二海堂(にかいどう)晴信(はるのぶ)）あっ 兄者(あにじゃ)っ！
（島田）ん？
Big Brother!
What did you come here for, kiddo?
どうして来たんだ 坊
You don't have a match today.
今日 お前は
対局じゃないだろう？
Sorry, Big Brother.
すみません 兄者
How's your fever?
熱は… まだ あるじゃないか
You still have one.
You need to take care.
大事にしてないと…
昇級が かかっているんだぞ！
Your promotion is on the line.
You promised both your teacher and me you wouldn't overdo it, remember?
無理はしないって約束したろ？
俺とも師匠とも
In exchange, we promised we wouldn't tell anyone.
みんなには言わないって
約束と引き換えに
Yes. I'll head home and lie down.
はい　すぐに戻って
横になります
Sorry.
すみません
うん いや俺も…
Actually, me too.
Sorry for getting on your case like that.
いきなり
やいやい言ってすまない
I was just surprised to see you here.
びっくりしてな お前がいるから
So why are you here, kiddo?
で どうしたんだ？ 坊
Is there something you wanted to tell me?
何か 俺に
伝えたいことでもあったのか？
Yes. Actually, Big Brother...
はい　実は兄者…
I want you to...
（二海堂）兄者に…
（島田）ん？
split Kiriyama's head in half.
桐山の頭を
かち割ってやってほしいのです
Dang it, kiddo.
（島田）坊のやつ
何を言うかと思えば また…
I was wondering what you were going to say.
やっかいなことを…
You've really put me in a pickle.
（島田）さて と…
Well, then...
Shall we continue?
じゃあ 続けようか
On the Other Side of the Door
Your fingers, your chest, your eyes
Are so dazzling there are nights when I get dizzy
They suddenly fall upon me, and it's just so warm
That it feels like I swallowed a seven-colored star
You held me tight, troubling me like a burning spark would
But I was taught to keep walking despite everything
God, please hear me out
For just a little while
Please connect us like that constellation
So that we're never away from each other
So that we're always together
Next Episode Preview
Episode 14
Who eats cold food
when they're depressed?
（林田(はやしだ)）
落ち込んでるときに—
冷たいもの
食ってるやつがあるか
Otherwise you'll lose half your HP!
ヒットポイントが
半分に なっちまうんだぞ
Is that how it is?
（二海堂）
そういうものなのですか
What do I do?
（零）どうしよう
何か分かんなくなってきた
I feel like I don't know anymore.
Well...
（島田）じゃあ ここから
ちょっと進めてみようか
Why don't we replay a bit from here?
Illustration: Azuma Kiyohiko
（二海堂）３月のライオン
いよいよ兄者が登場！
At long last, Big Brother appears in
"March comes in like a lion"!
You'll watch our brotherly love, right?
兄者と俺の師弟愛
見てくれよな！
Big Brother!
兄者〜！